James Slater Papers 1998.0367
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
James Slater Papers
1937-2004
1998.0367
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
18.95 Linear feet
The James Slater papers documents Slater's career as a world renowned entomologist and faculty member at the University of Connecticut from 1953 until his retirement in 1988. The correspondence, diaries, notes, records, photographs and other materials also reflect Slater's research on milk glass and colonial gravestones.
Slater, James
Biography
James Slater was born on January 10, 1920, in Belvidere, Illinois, and spent his childhood in Rockford, Illinois. After receiving his bachelor's and master's degrees at the University of Illinois, Slater earned his Ph.D. in entomology at Iowa State University. A world renowned expert in entomology, Slater joined the University of Connecticut faculty in 1953 and retired in 1988. Slater was an expert on heteropteran insects, also known as "true bugs," or more commonly, "typical bugs." He published his research on the topic in A Catalogue of the Lygaeidae in 1964. His interest in insects brought him around the world, and he collected insects in Africa, Australia, Central America and the West Indies.
While at UConn, Professor Slater served as the head of the zoology and entomology departments, and as head of the systematic and evolutionary biology and biological sciences group. He also served as president of the Society of Systematic Zoology, the Connecticut Chapters of Phi Beta Kappa, the Connecticut Entomological Society, and as the Connecticut State Ornithologist.
Slater's research interests extended outside of entomology. He also applied his scholarly attentions to the study of gravestones and milk glass, and published books on both topics.
James Slater died in 2008.
Scope and Content Note
The collection includes materials relating to James Slater's career in entomology, and his research into gravestones and other interests. The collection is comprised of books, diaries, correspondence, manuscripts, notes, clippings, administrative records, publications, ephemera, and photographs, as well as other materials from 1937 to 2004. The range of materials will allow researchers to explore Slater's work on entomology and gravestones throughout his career.
Subjects related to his research into entomology include a manuscript of Catalog of the Lygaeidae of the World, by James Slater and J. O'Donnell, the Entomological Journal Antenna: Bulletin of the Royal Entomological Society of London (nearly complete run of issues from 1977 to 2001), the Entomological Society of London, World War II, Okinawa, University of Connecticut, Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, various works by James Slater, British Museum of Natural History, American Museum of Natural History, University of Queensland, Australia, California Academy of Sciences Annual Report 1980-1981, National Geographic Society, Connecticut State Museum of Natural History, Hemiptera, Heteroptera, and numerous other materials related to the bugs he studied.
In addition to materials related to the study of bugs, the collection includes subjects related to his interests in gravestones. Some of these subjucts include the Association for Gravestone Studies, the Connecticut Academy for Arts and Sciences, the American Gravestone Society, Connecticut State Archaeologist; Nicholas Bellantoni, Connecticut State Archaeology and History, Connecticut and New England History, and historic cemeteries in many of Connecticut's towns and cities.
Historical figures discussed in relation to his research on gravestones include Moses Cleveland, Nathaniel Hodgkins, John Hartshorne, Obadiah Wheeler, Jotham Warren, and the Loomis Family (Gravestone Carvers). Also included are publications and manuscripts written by Slater related to the study of gravestones, to include A Study of the Colonial Gravestone Carvings of Obadiah Wheeler of Lebanon, Connecticut, Jotham Warren, the Plainfield Trumpeter, Colonial Burying Grounds of Eastern Connecticut and the Men Who Made Them, Tomb with a View, and Color on Gravestones.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Provenance and Acquisition
The records were donated by James Slater in several installments beginning in 1998.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to various aspects of Connecticut history, Connecticut's flora, fauna and environment, and the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the Reading Room desk.
Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Connecticut -- History.; Connecticut--Family and personal papers--20th century.; Publications.; University Archives; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut.; University of Connecticut—Faculty.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives--Connecticut.
- Series I: An Inventory, 1937-2004; 18.95 Linear feet
  - Books (diaries), notes, clippings, 1937-1940, 1942-1943, 1945, 1960, 1962, 1965, 1971, 1977, 1982-1983, 1987, 1990, 1991, 2001, 2002; 1.3 Linear feet (Box 1)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Subjects Include: Life Sciences Faculty, Entomology, Lygaeidae, Hemiptera, Heteroptera, Connecticut Gravestones, Africa, Europe, World War II, Okinawa.]
    University of Connecticut.; University of Connecticut—Faculty.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.; World War, 1939-1945--Connecticut --Personal narratives.
  - Publications, books (diaries), transcripts, clippings, correspondences, manuscripts, photographs (insects), map ( Madagascar), 1943, 1945, 1974, 1979, 1980-1982, 1985, 1993-1995, 1998-1999, 2002-2004; 1.3 Linear feet (Box 2)
    [Subjects Include: World War II, Okinawa, University of Connecticut, Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, Connecticut Agricultural Experiment Station, Habitats of New England Insects and The Meadow by James Slater, Entomology, American Museum of Natural History, National Geographic Society, Edith Marion Patch, South Africa, Genus Cattarus, Lygaeidae, Hemiptera, Entomological Society of America.]
    Agricultural experiment stations—Connecticut.; Biologists--Connecticut.; Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Ecology--Study and teaching.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.; World War, 1939-1945--Connecticut --Personal narratives.; World War, 1939-1945--Personal narratives--Connecticut.; World War, 1939-1945—Personal narratives—Connecticut.
  - Correspondence, publications, administrative records, financial records, notes, postcards, undated, 1986, 1991-1994; 0.25 Linear feet folders (Box 3a)
    [Subjects Include: Connecticut State Museum of Natural History, Center for Systematic Entomology, Inc., Entomology, Life Sciences Faculty, Mansfield Center, Connecticut, Residents, Leotichius, Lygaeidae, Xyonysius, Joseph Vincent McHugh.]
    Ecology--Study and teaching.; Storrs (Conn.); Storrs (Conn.)--Education--Universities and colleges.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Professional and personal papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.
  - Correspondence, manuscripts, photographs (facsimiles), clippings, transcripts, map ( Massachusetts; Middlefield, Connecticut), sketches (gravestone designs), ephemera, publications, 1981, 1985-1988, 1990-1996, 1998; 0.5 Linear feet folders (Box 3b)
    [Subjects Include: Historical Gravestones, Gravestone Study, Life Sciences Faculty, American Gravestone Society, Glastonbury, Wethersfield, Suffield, and Windsor, Connecticut, Nicholas Bellantoni, Connecticut State Archaeology and History, International Genealogical Index, Hampton Indian Carver, Tree Stump Carver (Unknown Gravestone Carver Nicknames), Manuscripts and Publications: James Stancliff in Yorkshire, England by Sherry Stancliff, John Huntington and Inscriptions: St. James Lot: Mount Auburn Cemetery January 1996.]
    Connecticut -- History.; Connecticut Cities and towns History.; History--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.
  - Correspondence, photographs, postcards, manuscripts, notes, transcripts, administrative records, undated, 1966-1967, 1969, 1971, 1973, 1975-1976, 1979, 1985, 1998; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 4)
    [Subjects Include: Life Sciences Faculty, Lygaeidae, Hemiptera, Heteroptera, Entomology, West Indies, French Antilles, Insect Flightlessness, James Slater Lecture "West Indian Lygaeidae Biogeography," James Slater publication Lygaeidae of the French Antilles, French Publication Catalogue Raisonne Des Insectes Des Antilles Francaises.]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Molecular biology--Study and teaching.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.
  - Correspondence (alphabetized A-G), administrative records, manuscripts, ephemera, financial records, 1941, 1947, 1951, 1953-1957, 1969-1973, 1975-1976, 1978, 1981, 1983, 1985, 1988; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 5)
    [Subjects Include: Lygaeidae, Hemiptera, Life Sciences Faculty, Entomological Research, Entomology Faculty Newsletter, Charles O. Esselbaugh Insect Collection (inventory list), American Museum of Natural History, Peter D. Ashlock, How to Know the True Bugs by James Slater.]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Ecology--Study and teaching.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.
  - Correspondence (alphabetized G-P), ephemera, administrative records, manuscripts, notes, financial records, 1949, 1952, 1956-1957, 1959, 1962-1963, 1968-1969, 1974-1975, 1977-1978, 1984-1985; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 6)
    [Subjects Include: Entomological Society of America, Imperial Institute of Entomology, British Museum of Natural History, R. J. Izzard (correspondence), Lygaeidae, Hemiptera, Psychoidae (common moth fly), Life Sciences Faculty, Entomology, Article Manuscript "A Reconstruction of the Status of the Ischnodemus Sabuleti Complex (Hemiptera: Lygaeidae) by James Slater.]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Mansfield (Conn.); Mansfield (Conn.)—Resident of.; Mansfield Center (Conn.); Publications.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.
  - Correspondence (alphabetized P-Z), administrative records, clippings, publications, fliers, financial records, ephemera, manuscripts, 1957-1958, 1974, 1975, 1977-1978, 1981, 1985, 1987, 1992-1993; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 7)
    [Subjects Include: James Slater, South Africa Expedition (1974), Entomology, Life Sciences Faculty, Department of Zoology and Evolutionary Biology, Trail Woods, Edwin Way Teale Memorial Sanctuary, Articles "Nature at its Finest: The Edwin Way Teale Collection" By John P. McDonald, "Trail Wood: Hampton, Connecticut: An Ecological Survey of the Edwin Way Teale Memorial Nature Sanctuary," and "Vegetation of the Edwin Way Teale Sanctuary."]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Edwin Teale.; Edwin Way Teale.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Professional and personal papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.
  - Administrative records, ephemera, financial records, manuscripts, transcripts, publications, undated, 1965-1966, 1973, 1975, 1977-1978, 1983-1991; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 8)
    Subjects Include: Entomology, Life Sciences Faculty, American Museum of Natural History, Hemiptera, Lygaeidae, Terrapene, Publication "Foundations for a National Biological Survey," Article manuscript "Icarus Revisited, or, Why it is Good to Lose Your Wings" by James Slater, Carl Schaefer, Ozophora, Heteroptera, Pentatomidae
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Draft Publications.; Publications.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.
  - Books, publications, correspondence, administrative records, transcripts, notes, 1953, 1965, 1968, 1970, 1979, 1989, 2000; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 9)
    [Subjects Include: University of Connecticut, Gulley Hall (facsimile plan), Life Sciences Faculty, Entomology, Zoology and Evolutionary Biology, Proposal for National Science Foundation Science Development Program: Environmental Studies, Specifications for Environmental Science Facilities, University of Connecticut, Survey of the Environmental Sciences at the University of Connecticut by N.T. Davis, Connecticut River Microbiology Oct. 1965-Sep. 1969 by John D. Buck; Speech "Two Cultures Revisited," Talks by James Slater "Changes in the Status of New England Birds," "Phylogeny of the Family Miridae," "What is Happening to Mr. Bueno's Bugs," "Teaching of Entomology and Zoology in American Universities," "White Man's Africa: A Perspective on South Africa"]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; College presidents--Connecticut.; Research.; Speeches.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut.; University of Connecticut—Presidents.
  - Correspondence, notes, manuscripts, financial records, administrative records, postcards, publications, 1964-1965, 1969, 1975-1976, 1978-1980, 1982; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 10)
    [Subjects Include: British Museum of Natural History, Lygaeidae, Entomology, Entomological Research, Life Sciences Faculty, University of Connecticut, American Museum of Natural History, University of Queensland, Australia, Manuscript for "The Morphology and Higher Systematics of the Idiostlinae (Heteroptera: Lygaeidae) With a Description of the Fourth-Instance Nymph" by Carl W. Schaefer, Brooklyn College, Dr. Reece I. Sailer, European Parasite Laboratory, Ischnodemus, Hemiptera, National Science Foundation, Manuscript for "Orius insidiosus (Say) (Hemiptera: Anthocoridae) Biting White-footed Mice" by W. L. Krinsky, A. B. Carey and Marion G. Carey, California Academy of Sciences Annual Report 1980-1981.]
    Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Draft Publications.; Publications.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut.
  - Publications, transcript, 1943, 1946, 1948-1949, 1952, 1965, 1969-1974, 1977, 1981, 1983, 1985, 1986-1988, 1995, 1997; 1.3 Linear feet bagged (Box 11)
    [Subjects Include: Life Sciences Faculty, Entomology, Entomological Study, Hemiptera, Heteroptera, Entomological Publications by James Slater on species of Lygaeidae, including Ischnodemus fieber, Lygaeus kalmii, Macropes hoberlandti, Catorhintha mendica, Lachnestes singalensis, etc., including discussions of Blissinae and Rhyparochrominae; Transcript of speech "The Responsibilities of the Insect Taxonomist" by James Slater.]
    Biologists--Connecticut.; Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Publications.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Professional and personal papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut.
  - Notes, manuscripts, correspondence, postcards, publications, clippings, undated, 1954, 1962, 1968, 1970, 1972, 1975, 1978-1982, 1987; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 12)
    [Subjects Include: Connecticut and New England History, Gravestones, American History, Life Sciences Faculty, Historic Cemeteries in the towns of Ashford, Bolton, Bozrah, Brooklyn, Canterbury, Chaplin, Colchester, Columbia, Coventry, Eastford, East Hampton, East Hartford, East Windsor, East Lyme, Ellington, Enfield, Franklin, Glastonbury, Griswold, Groton, Hampton, Hebron, Killingly, Lebanon, Ledyard, Lisbon, Manchester, Mansfield, Marlborough, Montville, North Stonington, Norwich, Old Lyme, Plainfield, Pomfret, Portland, Preston, Putnam, Salem, Scotland, Somes, South Windsor, Sprague, Stafford, Sterling, Stonington, Thompson, Tolland, Union, Vernon, Voluntown Waterford, Windham, and Woodstock; Historical Figures Moses Cleveland, Nathaniel Hodgkins, John Hartshorne, Obadiah Wheeler, Jotham Warren, Loomis Family (Gravestone Carvers); A Study of the Colonial Gravestone Carvings of Obadiah Wheeler of Lebanon, Connecticut by James Slater and Ernest Caulfield, The Art of Gravestone Hunting by Randall T. Schuh, Jotham Warren, the Plainfield Trumpeter by James Slater, extensive manuscript of Colonial Burying Grounds of Eastern Connecticut and the Men Who Made Them by James Slater; Enicocephalomorpha, Lygaeidae.]
    Connecticut—History, Local.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut.; University of Connecticut—Faculty—Professional and personal papers. English language—Study and teaching (Higher)—Connecticut.
  - Publications, 1985-1999; 1.3 Linear feet ordered by date (Box 13)
    [Subjects Include: Entomology, Entomological and Biological Scientific Journals and Publications Insecta Mundi, Journal of African Zoology, and Insects in African Economy and Environment.]
    Africa.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Publications.; South Africa.
  - Correspondence (alphabetized D-W; regarding gravestones), ephemera, manuscripts, galley proofs, postcards, fliers, publications, notes, clippings, map, facsimile photographs, 1976, 1984-1987, 1992-1993, 1995-1999; 1.3 Linear feet folders (Box 14)
    [Subjects Include: Connecticut History, Historical Gravestones, Association for Gravestone Studies, Connecticut Academy for Arts and Sciences, Connecticut Historical Society, The Colonial Burying Grounds of Eastern Connecticut by James Slater, Tomb with a View, Color on Gravestones by James Slater, Gravestones by Kevin M. Sweeney, Graveboard newsletter, The Pratt Family of Stone Cutters by Ralph Tucker, Gravestones of Joseph Sikes; Gravestone Carvers Obadiah Wheeler, Jotham Warren, Joseph Sikes.]
    Connecticut -- History.; Connecticut—History, Local.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.; University of Connecticut-Faculty-Personal and professional papers.
  - Manuscripts, publications, notes, undated, 1960, 1977-2001; 1.3 Linear feet ordered by date (Box 15)
    [Subjects Include: Life Sciences Faculty, Entomology, Entomological Research, Publication Manuscript "Catalog of the Lygaeidae of the World," by James Slater and J. O'Donnell, Antenna: Bulletin of the Royal Entomological Society of London (nearly complete run of issues from 1977 to 2001) Entomological Society of London, Hemiptera, Heteroptera.]
    Biologists--Connecticut.; Biology teachers--Connecticut.; Biology--Research--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching--Connecticut.; Biology--Study and teaching.; Proofs.; Publications.; University of Connecticut--Faculty--Personal and professional papers.; University of Connecticut--Faculty.